Guide to the Office of Minority Affairs records, 1969-1993 UA.09.08.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of Minority Affairs records
1969-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Office of Minority Affairs
UA.09.08.0001
16.8 Linear Feet
Since its inception in 1969, the Office of Minority Affairs (formerly known as the Office of Black Affairs and currently the Office of Intercultural Affairs) has primarily addressed the needs of the African American student population at Duke University, providing an organizational structure through which Black participation in the University and local communities can obtain the greatest degree of effectiveness. The collection contains a variety of administrative materials, including reports, correspondence, minutes and programs, documenting the directives and activities of the Office of Minority Affairs. Also included are materials pertaining to the Summer Transitional Program, which was established in 1969 and managed by the Office of Minority Affairs.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their educational records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Office of Minority Affairs records were received by the University Archives as a transfer from 1977-2005.
Historical Note
Since its inception in 1969, the Office of Minority Affairs (formerly known as the Office of Black Affairs and currently the Office of Intercultural Affairs) has primarily addressed the needs of the African American student population at Duke University. Created soon after the Afro-American Society students led a Black student takeover of the Allen Building to spark University action on the concerns of Black students, the core mission of the Office of Black Affairs was to provide outreach to black students to facilitate rapid involvement with the university community through mentorship programs, financial aid, academic counseling and tutoring, and the development of Black Studies courses. Under some controversy, the name was changed to the Office of Minority Affairs in 1978. While the name had changed, the core mission of the office remained the same, which was to provide an organizational structure through which Black participation in the University and local communities obtained the greatest degree of effectiveness.
One of the more prominent programs of the Office of Minority Affairs was the Summer Transitional Program (STP). Initiated in 1969 as one of the ten demands made of the University following the occupation of the Allen Building, the experimental program was designed to facilitate the student's transition from the secondary level to the demands of the university level. With the original goal of decreasing the attrition rate of black students by raising the level of academic performance and introducing the students to the social structures of Duke University at a very early date, in the early 1970's the focus of STP changed to assist all students, no matter their ethnic group, in their transition to university life.
Collection Overview
The Office of Minority Affairs' records spans the years 1969-1993. The collection is arranged into three series: Administrative Records, 1969-1993; Scrapbooks, 1968-1991; and Summer Transitional Program, 1969-1986.
Materials in the collection include administrative records, correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, course schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, financial information, photographs, programs, scrapbooks, and other materials from the Office of Minority Affairs.
Related Material
Inventory of African and African American Studies records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Allen Building Takeover, 1969-2002.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948-2001 and undated.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Black Student Alliance records, 1969-2002.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Student Project for University Development records, 1976-1979.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Trinity College of Arts and Sciences, Office of the Dean records, 1934-2003.
University Archives, Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
College students, Black -- North Carolina; Students, Black -- North Carolina; African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American student movements; Duke University. Office of Minority Affairs; Duke University. Office of Black Affairs; Duke University. Office of Intercultural Affairs; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Duke University. Afro-American Society; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- Curricula; Duke University -- Administration
- Administrative Records, 1969-1993, 12 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  These files consist of a variety of administrative materials, including reports, correspondence, minutes and programs, documenting the directives and activities of the Office of Minority Affairs. These activities, which include recruitment of minority students, financial and community relations, campus life (cultural/social activities), academic counseling and tutoring, and the development of Black Studies courses, were meant to address the individual and collective concerns within the minority student population at Duke University.
  - AAS (Afro-American Society), 1969 (Box 1)
  - AAS, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - AAS, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - AAS, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Academic Council and Provost Group, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Active File - Turner, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Admission and Recruitment of Black Students, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Admissions Study Committee, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Advising and Other Issues, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Advising - Turner, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee Meeting, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Council to OBA (Office of Black Affairs), 1974 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Alumni Project, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1974-1981 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies Articles, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Information, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Association of African Students, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Athletes, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Black Alumni, 1981-1990 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory, 1974-1975, 1975-1976, 1976-1977, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (General Directory of Afro-American Students), 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (Black Undergraduate Directory), 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (Directory of Black Undergraduate and Graduate Students), 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (Directory of Black Undergraduate/Graduate Students and Faculty/Administrators), 1982-1983, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (Directory of Black Undergraduate/Graduate Students and Faculty/Administrators), 1985-1986, 1986-1987, 1987-1988, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Black Directory (Directory of Black Undergraduate/Graduate Students and Faculty/Administrators), 1989-1990, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Blacks: Education, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Black Enrollment, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Black Graduate and Professional Student Caucus, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Black Graduate and Professional Student Caucus Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Black Graduate Caucus Constitutions, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Black Graduates, 1984-1991 (Box 3)
  - Black Graduate/Professional Students, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Black Greeks, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Black Greeks, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Black Greeks, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Black Greeks, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Black Greeks, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Black Politics and Organizations in Durham and Area, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Black Seminarian's Union, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A. (Black Student Alliance), 1978 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1979 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - B.S.A., 1982-1984 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1986 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1987 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - B.S.A., 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Black Students Organizations, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Black Students and Program Research Projects, News Stories, etc., 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - Black Student Weekend, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Black Studies, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Black Studies, 1971 July-1972 July (Box 4)
  - Black Studies, 1972 August-1973 January (Box 4)
  - Black Studies (Turner), 1974-1978 (Box 4)
  - Black Studies at Other Colleges/Universities, 1969-1973 (Box 4)
  - Black Studies Course Outlines, 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - Black Studies Proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Black/White Relations, 1980-1983 (Box 5)
  - Black/White Relations Notes, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Black/White Relations Task Force, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Borens, John (Dean of Office of Black Affairs), 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Career's Day, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Communications, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
  - Conferences and Issues in Black Higher Education, 1970-1973 (Box 5)
  - CASA (Counseling in Academic and Social Affairs), 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - CASA, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - CASA/BSA Peer Counseling, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - CASA Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - CASA Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
  - CASA Evaluation, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - CASA Final Report, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - CASA Final Report, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - CASA Final Report, 1982-1983, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - CASA Manuals, 1977-1978, 1978-1979, 1979-1980, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - CASA Manuals, 1981-1982, 1982-1983, 1983-1984, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - CASA Manuals, 1985-1986, 1986-1987, 1988-1989, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - CASA Memorandum, 1985-1986 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1976 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1977 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1978 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - CASA Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 7)
  - CASA Evaluation, 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - CASA Proposals, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - CASA Proposals, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - CASA Tutorial Program, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Cultural Center - Afro-Americans, undated (Box 7)
  - Duke Review, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Awards, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Fein, John (Dean), Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 7)
  - Financial Aid, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - General Information, 1978, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Grapevine, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Graduate Awards, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
  - Greek Organizations, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - Griffith, William (Vice President), 1982-1984 (Box 8)
  - Griffith, William, Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 8)
  - Iota Mu Reunion, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Inter-office Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
  - Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
  - Job Description - Graduate Assistant, undated (Box 8)
  - Job Description - Dean of Black Affairs, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Kappa Alpha Psi, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - Kappa Alpha Psi, 1986-1988 (Box 8)
  - Lattimore, Carol (Dean), Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
  - Letters (incoming), 1974-1977 (Box 8)
  - Math Proposal, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Minority Staff at Other Universities, 1978-1985 (Box 8)
  - National Black Political Agenda, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Newspapers, 1969-1972 (Box 9)
  - Office of Black Affairs, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Office of Black Affairs: Working Documents, 1972 (Box 9)
  - OMA (Office of Minority Affairs), 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - OMA Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - OMA Evaluation Report, 1976 (Box 9)
  - OMA Goals and Objectives, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - OMA Resource Guide, 1980-1983 (Box 9)
  - OMA Staff, 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - OMA Staff Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - OMA Statistics, 1978-1980 (Box 9)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1976-1977 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1978-1979 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1981-1983 (Box 10)
  - Office of Black Affairs: Working Documents, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1986-1987 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1987-1988 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1988-1989 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1990-1991 (Box 10)
  - Printed Materials, 1989-1993 (Box 10)
  - Prometheus Black, 1978, 1985, 1989, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Race Relations Reporter, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
  - Recruitment of Black Graduates, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholarship, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1983-1984 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1984-1986 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1986-1987 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
  - Reggie Howard Scholars, 1988-1991 (Box 11)
  - Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
  - Report: Programs CASA and the Tutoring Program, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
  - Report to the Presidents Council on Black Affairs, 1985 (Box 12)
  - Reports: Of or relating to the Office of Black Affairs, 1970-1971 (Box 12)
  - Recruitment of Black Graduates, 1971-1973 (Box 12)
  - Roots (Articles), 1979 (Box 12)
  - Soul City, 1971 (Box 12)
  - Student Affairs, 1991-1992 (Box 12)
  - Subcommittee on Summer Awards: Undergraduates, 1971-1973 (Box 12)
  - TCAS Excellence Program, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Turner, William (Dean) Administration, 1976-1977 (Box 12)
  - TUCAP, undated (Box 12)
  - Tutorial Program, 1976-1977 (Box 12)
  - Tutoring, 1974-1977 (Box 12)
  - Duke Preview Program, final report, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Duke Preview Program, final report, 1989 (Box 12)
  - Report to the President's Council on Black Affairs on the Office of Minority Affiars, 1985 (Box 12)
  - Report to the President's Council on Black Affairs reprint, 1985 (Box 12)
- Scrapbooks, 1968-1991, 4 boxes
  The scrapbooks consist primarily of newspaper clippings recording events related to the Office of Minority Affairs and the minority student population at Duke University. The clippings are primarily from the Duke Media, but also include some from other newspapers, such as the Carolina Times and the Durham Herald. Also included are various flyers produced by black student organizations at Duke University.
  - Scrapbooks, 1968-1976 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1977- 1979 March (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1979 Apr-Dec (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1983 Jan-Jun (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1983 Jul-Dec (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1984 Jan-Jun (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1984 Jul-Dec (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1985 Jan-Jun (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1985 Jul-Dec (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1986 Jan-Apr (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1986 May-Dec (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1987 Jan-Jun (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1987 Jul-Dec (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1988 Jan-Mar (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1988 Apr-Jun (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1988 Ju1-Dec (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1989 Jan-Jun (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks, 1989 Jul-Dec (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 1990 Jan-Apr (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 1990 May-Oct (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 1990 Nov - 1991 Apr (Box 16)
- Summer Transitional Program, 1969-1986, 8 boxes
  These files consist of a variety of materials pertaining to the Summer Transitional Program, which was established and managed by the Office of Minority Affairs. Materials include evaluation reports, correspondence, minutes, brochures, applications from prospective students and residential advisor, and statistics.
  Conditions Governing Access
  In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their educational records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
  - Academic Orientation, 1969 (Box 17)
  - Admissions & Information, 1970 (Box 17)
  - Advisors and Consultants, 1969-1973 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee, 1975-1978 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee, 1982 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee, 1983 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Committee Minutes, 1986 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Council, 1979 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Council, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Council, 1979-1981 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Council, 1980-1981 (Box 17)
  - Applicants, 1972 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Applicant Information and other Information, 1974 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1975 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1976 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1977 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1978 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1982 (Box 18)
  - Applicants, 1983 (Box 19)
  - Applicants, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Applicants, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Applicants, 1986 (Box 19)
  - Applicants Not Attending, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Applicants Not Attending, 1979-1983 (Box 19)
  - Banquets, 1977-1986 (Box 19)
  - Brochures, 1970-1971, 1973-1976, 1978-1986 (Box 19)
  - Co-curricular Activities, 1983 (Box 19)
  - Course Content, 1979-1981 (Box 19)
  - Curriculum Review Committee, 1979-1985 (Box 19)
  - Evaluation [of STP] by Dr. Michael Michlin, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Evaluation [of STP], 1969-1970 (Box 19)
  - Evaluation [of STP], 1972-1979 (Box 20)
  - Evaluation [of STP by Student Advisors], 1969-1972 (Box 20)
  - Evaluations [Student Responses to STP], 1969 (Box 20)
  - Evaluations [Student Responses to STP], 1979-1980 (Box 20)
  - Evaluations [Student Responses to STP], 1981-1982 (Box 20)
  - Evaluations [of STP Students by Professors/Student Advisors], 1969-1973 (Box 20)
  - Evaluations and Recommendations [of STP], 1969-1970 (Box 20)
  - Executive Staff Minutes, 1979 (Box 20)
  - Expenses, 1969-1971 (Box 20)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1977-1978 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1979 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff [Recommendations], 1979 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1980 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1981 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1983-1984 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff, 1985-1986 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meetings, 1980 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meetings, 1981 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meetings, 1982 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meetings, 1983 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meeting Minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Meeting Minutes, 1986 (Box 21)
  - Faculty and Staff Minutes, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Final Report, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Final Report, 1970, 1974, 1975 (Box 21)
  - Final Report, 1976 (Box 22)
  - Final Reports and Comments [Faculty and Staff], 1979 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1979 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1980 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1981 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1982 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1983 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1984 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1985 (Box 22)
  - Final Report, 1986 (Box 22)
  - Forms, 1981-1983 (Box 22)
  - Freshmen Perspectives, 1979 (Box 22)
  - General Information, 1977-1978 (Box 22)
  - Handbooks, 1978-1986 (Box 23)
  - History of STP (Box 23)
  - Housing - Social & Dining, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Housing - Social & Dining, 1973 (Box 23)
  - Meal Plans, 1983-1986 (Box 23)
  - Participants, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Participants, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Participants, 1980-1983 (Box 23)
  - Photograph, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Planning Session Workshops (Counselors), 1979 (Box 23)
  - Planning Session Workshops (Counselors), 1980 (Box 23)
  - Questionnaires, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Questionnaires, 1970 (Box 23)
  - Residential Advisors Interviews, 1984-1986 (Box 23)
  - Residential Advisors Memoranda, 1984 (Box 23)
  - Statistical Information, 1979-1981 (Box 23)
  - STP in the News, 1969-1971 (Box 23)
  - STP Review [by Bryant and DeMarchi], 1985-1986 (Box 24)
  - Study Skills, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Study Skills Packet, 1985 (Box 24)
  - Summer Transitional Program, 1971 (Box 24)
  - Summer Transitional Program, 1976-1978 (Box 24)
  - Summer Transitional Program, 1981 (Box 24)
  - Summer Transitional Program, 1981-1982 (Box 24)
  - Syllabi for STP Courses, 1984-1985 (Box 24)
  - Turner Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 24)